Guide to the E. Wight Bakke papers, 1929-1971 [bulk 1945-1970].
Bakke, E. Wight papers, 1929-1971 [bulk 1945-1970].
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
E. Wight Bakke papers 1929-1971 [bulk 1945-1970].
5960
Bakke, E. Wight (Edward Wight), 1903-
4.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, bibliographies, publications, subject files, minutes, and reports.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, manuscripts, pamphlets, reviews, sermons, lectures, minutes and reports written by or about E. Wight Bakke, primarily during his years as professor at Yale University.
4.5 cubic feet
E. Wight Bakke, management theorist and professor, Yale University Labor and Management Center.
E. Wight Bakke was born in Onawa, Iowa, to Harriet Frances (Wight) and Oscar Christian Bakke, a shoe merchant in Onawa. Bakke attended Northwestern University where he received a BA in Philosophy in 1926. He continued in the Yale Divinity School from 1926 to 1929 and during that time was also a pastor of the Park Methodist Episcopal Church. His graduate study in social sciences was also conducted at Yale University, and from 1931-1932 he was the Sterling Fellow at Yale, receiving his Ph.D. in 1932. In 1964 he received an honorary LL. D. from Northwestern University.
Bakke taught sociology at Yale from 1932-1934, and was an assistant professor of economics from 1934-1938. He served the Institute of Human Relations as Director of Unemployment Studies from 1934-1939, and was promoted to Professor of Economics in 1938 and appointed the Sterling Professor of Economics in 1940. Bakke was the Director of Graduate Studies in Economics at Yale from 1940-1950. From 1944 until the late 1950's he directed Yale's Labor and Management Center. The Center was devised with a nine-member policy committee made up of three representatives of Yale, three from labor, and three from management to develop a balanced approach and avoid an "ivory tower" view of labor relations.
Bakke was often called upon to advise governmental commissions and scholarly organizations on labor and management issues. He was Fulbright professor in Denmark in 1953, the principal consulting social economist for the Social Security Board from 1936-1939, and a consultant to the Department of Labor, Navy Department. He directed the National Bureau of Economic Research, and was the Chairman of the Appeals Committee of the National War Labor Board. He was a member of several Presidential Emergency Boards and the National Manpower Policy Task Force.
Correspondence, manuscripts, pamphlets, reviews, sermons, lectures, minutes and reports written by or about E. Wight Bakke, primarily during his years as professor at Yale University.
Among the topics covered in this collection are: the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University, including correspondence on the founding of the school; manuscripts, reviews, and correspondence of or about Bakke's many publications; the Yale Labor and Management Center; reports on the graduate education of women at Yale; Bakke's teaching materials; articles by Bakke on industrial relations, management, manpower policy, organizational behavior, and student movements; and minutes and reports from task forces, professional boards, and committees, including the National Manpower Policy Task Force and the New York State Public Employment Relations Board (PERB).
Bakke, E. Wight; Bakke, E. Wight (Edward Wight), 1903-; National Manpower Policy Task Force.; New York (State) Public Employment Relations Board.; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations.; Yale University--Faculty.; Yale University Labor and Management Center.; Yale University--Graduate work.
Industrial relations--Study and teaching--United States.; Industrial management--Study and teaching--United States.; Manpower policy.; Student movements.; Organizational behavior.; Women graduate students--Connecticut--New Haven.; College teachers
Correspondence; Pamphlets; Reviews; Sermons; Lectures; Manuscripts; Minutes; Reports
Publications are arranged alphabetically by title. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by subject. Professional board, task force, and committee files are arranged by national, and then state and local levels.
5522. E. Wight Bakke. Papers.
Series I. Biographical material.
Box 1
Series II. Correspondence.
A. General correspondence.
Box 1
B. Correspondence regarding Bakke's publications.
Box 1
C. Editorial correspondence.
Box 1
D. Reviews of Bakke's publications.
Box 1
Series III. Yale University
A. Yale Labor and Management Center (LMC).
Box 1
B. Yale University teaching, research, and administration.
Box 1
Series IV. Publications.
Boxes 2-4
Series V. Subject files.
Box 4
Series VI. Professional boards, task forces, and committees.
Boxes 4-5
Series VII. Miscellaneous.
Box 5
- Series I. Biographical Material.
  Contains various iterations of E.W. Bakke's biographical sketch and publications lists.
  - Biographical sketches. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliographies. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II. Correspondence.
  - A. General correspondence.
    - A-H, Includes Cornell University Labor-Liberal Arts Student Association, and School of Industrial and Labor Relations re: school formation. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - I-N, Includes Charles Killingsworth re: the Detroit police wage arbitration; Charles A. Myers on unemployment; NY State School of Industrial and Labor Relations (NYSSILR) Dean's Office re: ILR School Council. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - O-Z, Includes correspondence to Robert Taggert, Executive Director, National Manpower Policy Task Force; Dr. M. H. Trytten, National Academy of Science; and to and from Rolf Waaler, Rector of Norges Handelshoyskole (in Norwegian). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Norwegian language correspondence and notes. (Box 1, Folder 5a)
    - Recommendations. (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - B. Correspondence regarding Bakke's publications.
    - The Mission of Manpower Policy - Includes comments by Solomon Barkin, January 1970. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Positive Labor Market Policy. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Revolutionary Democracy, Challenge and Testing in Japan. Correspondence in preparation for research, January - July 1963. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Revolutionary Democracy, Challenge and Testing in Japan. (Box 1, Folder 13a-14)
    - Students on the March - includes a brief discussion of selected points in the manuscript by Robert C. Jones, Centro Cultural Internacional, Mexico. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - C. Editorial correspondence.
    - Campus Challenge (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Revolutionary Democracy, Challenge and Testing in Japan. 1966, 1968. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Student Protest" - re. Encyclopedia of Education article. 1968-1970. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Student Protest" - Editorial mark up. (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Students on the March - submission letters to various publishers. 1969-1970. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Unemployed Man. 1933, 1942. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous publications. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - D. Reviews of Bakke's publications.
    - Insurance or Dole? (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mutual Survival, the Goal of Unions and Management. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - A Norwegian Contribution to Management Development. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - A Positive Labor Market Policy: Policy Premises for the Development, Operation, and Integration of the Employment and Manpower Services. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Promoting Labor Peace." (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Revolutionary Democracy: Challenge and Testing in Japan. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "The Next Stage in Management." (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Series III. Yale University.
  Includes correspondence, reports, organizational documents, and administrative information.
  - A. Yale Labor and Management Center (LMC).
    - Correspondence, routine. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "Report of the Director." [1946] (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "The First Four Years: Report of the Director of the Yale Labor and Management Center to the President and Fellows of Yale University, June 15, 1949." (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - LMC foundation, theory and objectives (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "Statement of Policy." (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Management Directive Functions (Summary)." (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Organizational Structure and Dynamics. A Project of Research, Training, and Publication." 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Documents regarding the LMC's relationship with the Department of Industrial Administration. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "Theoretical Framework of Research in Organizational Behavior." 1954 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Facilitative documents (Box 1, Folder 40-47)
  - B. Yale University teaching, research, and administration.
    - Correspondence. (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Introduction. (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Draft. (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Draft duplicate. (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Draft duplicate of text only. (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Preliminary Comments on Tables. (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
    - Draft tables 1-5. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Draft tables 6-11. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Tables. (Box 1, Folder 57-58)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - "Graduate Education for Women at Yale: Excerpts from a Report." Ventures 9 (Fall 1969): 11-25. (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Commission to Study the Governance of Yale University. Misc. documents. May 1969 - November 1971. (Box 1, Folder 60a)
    - Teaching material. Contemporary Social Institutions. (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Teaching material. Economics. (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Teaching material. Modern Social Conditions. (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Teaching material. Social Adaptation. (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Teaching material. Unidentified class. File cards with class outline by session. (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Teaching materials on the labor movement and collective bargaining, strikes, manpower policy, and case work. (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Series IV. Publications.
  Includes Bakke's publications, lectures, speeches and sermons, as well as published reviews of his work.
  - An Active Manpower Policy and Economic Fluctuations. Manuscript draft and photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - An Active Manpower Policy and Economic Fluctuations. Typescript and photocopy draft with handwritten editing. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - An Active Manpower Policy and Economic Fluctuations. Photocopy draft with editing. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - An Active Manpower Policy and Economic Fluctuations. Edited typescript. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - An Active Manpower Policy and Economic Fluctuations. Photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - "An Active Positive Manpower Policy". OECD Active Manpower Policy International Management Seminar. Brussels, April 14-17, 1964. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Adaptive Human Behavior: An Outline For The Study of Human Relations In Industry. Third draft, March 1949. (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Adaptive Human Behavior: An Outline For The Study of Human Relations In Industry. Fourth draft, 1950. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Adaptive Human Behavior: An Outline For The Study of Human Relations in Industry, 1951. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Advertising and Character." Notes for a speech delivered to the New Hampshire Add Club, Nov. 1927 and to the Milford Rotary, Feb. 1928. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "America and the Beveridge Plan." Yale Review (Summer 1944): 642-647. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - "Aspects of The Process of Status, Rank and Role: Definition and Activation." (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "The Basic Test of Adequacy of Unemployment Compensation." A speech delivered at the Annual Meeting of The American Association for Social Security, April 1941. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Basic Tests of The Adequacy of Unemployment Insurance." (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "Bedriftens Informasjonsproblem I relasjon til sanfunnet." Bedrifts Okonomen 8 (Oktober 1953): 343-346. (Box 2, Folder 16a)
  - Bonds of Organization. Chapters 1-2. Edited photocopies. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bonds of Organization. Chapters 3-4. Edited photocopies. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bonds of Organization. Chapter 5. Edited photocopies. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bonds of Organization. Chapters 6-7 and Appendices. Edited photocopies. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "British Experience with Unemployment Compensation." In Addresses on Industrial Relations. Bureau of Industrial Relations Bulletin No. 6, Ann Arbor: University of Michigan, 1937. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "Building a Waterworks Team." In, Proceedings of the Fifty-first Annual Meeting, Pennsylvania Water Works Association, October 8-10, 1947. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Campus Challenge. Contents, Preface, Bibliography, Appendix and Index, edited. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Central Mission of Employment Services." Employment Service Conferences. Conference I. The Brookings Institution, January 30, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Collective Bargaining in a Competitive Economy." Proceedings, National Conference of Electric and Gas Utility Accountants, vol. 1. April 17-19, 1950. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Comments on Dunlop and Whyte's 'Framework for the Analysis of Industrial Relations': Two Views." Industrial and Labor Relations Review 3 (April 1950): 402-405. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Concept of the Social Organization 1959. (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
  - "Content of the Concepts. Processes and Bonds of Organization." Yale Labor and Management Center, December 1954. (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Coordination of Manpower Services: Some Important Premises." (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Concluding Remarks". Proceedings of the Industrial Relations Research Association Winter 1967: 196-97. (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Das dritte Gesetz." AGP Mitteilungen Arbeitsgemeinschaft zur Forderung der Partnerschaft in der Wirtschaft e. V. Nummer 6, II. Jahrgang, 1. Dezember 1954. Redaktion: Dr. Bruno Herrmann, Dusseldorf. (Box 2, Folder 32a)
  - "Economic and Social Reasons for an Active Manpower Policy." OECD International Trade Union Seminar on Active Manpower Policy. Report No. 1, September 17-20, 1963. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Economists and Unemployment." American Economic Review Proceedings 30 (February 1941): 294-300. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Effect of Increasing Hours of Work on Productivity, Absences, and Accidents." An Exploratory Study made for the Department of Labor and the War Production Board. Text. By E. Wight Bakke assisted by Ralph Wolf. (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - "Effect of Increasing Hours of Work on Productivity, Absences, and Accidents." An Exploratory Study made for the Department of Labor and the War Production Board. Tables. By E. Wight Bakke assisted by Ralph Wolf. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "The Employment Service, the Key Agency in a Positive Manpower and Employment Program." Testimony before the Holland Committee, Washington D.C. July 1964. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Employment Service Role in an Active Labor Market Policy." Employment Service Review, 1 (January-February 1964): 1-8. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Evidences of Effectiveness of the Several Bonds of Organization." (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - "The Function of Management". Chapter 8 in Human Relations and Modern Management, ed. Hugh-Jones, pp. 221-54. Amsterdam: North-Holland Publications, 1958. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "Frameworks of Reference in Industrial Relations Research." Panel presentation. Proceedings of the Conference, Training and Research in Industrial Relations: II. May 9-10, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - "The Hardening of Antagonisms in Labor Relations." Monthly Labor Review, Vol. 82 (March 1960): 257-61. Excerpted from E.W. Bakke's Presidential Address at the December 27-29, 1959 meeting of the Industrial Relations Research Association. (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - "How Do I know?" (A poem published under the pseudonym Edward Wight). The Christian Century, (October 1930): 1186. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "Human Behavior in Relations Between Management, Unions and Workers." Society for the Advancement of Management, Proceedings, Annual National Fall Conference on Human Relations, Pittsburgh, PA. (October 31, 1946): 18-28. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Intended Consequences of Bonds of Organization". Table only, pp. 7-9. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Labor and Management Look Ahead." In Reconciling Labor and Management Philosophies, American Management Association, Personnel Series Number 98, 1946, pp. 9-25. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Labor and Management Look At Each Other." Labor and Nation, (June-July 1946): 21-23, 48. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Laboratory for Labor Problems: Studies of Trade Unionism at Yale." The Yale Scientific Magazine (Summer 1941): 3-5. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Latin American Student Movement." Speech notes. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Det Lonner seg a ansette personalsjef." Bedrifts-Okomonem 7(September 1957): 293-294. (Box 3, Folder 6a)
  - "Maintenance of Organizational Stability and Viability." [1960]. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Management and Unions Look Ahead." First Draft. [1946]. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Mass Demonstrations." January 1967. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Memorandum to Students About to Become Industrial Nurses: Status, Role and Adjustment Problems of a Nurse in an Industrial Environment." March 1951. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Menschenfuhrung als Funktion der Unternehmensfuhrung." In Handbuch fur Manager August 1972: 201-216. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Mutual Survival After Twelve Years." Paper delivered as his Presidential address at the Annual Meeting of the Industrial Relations Research Association, December 1958. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - The Occupational Revolution: The Adaptation of the People of Japan to a New Day. Chapters 1-5. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - The Occupational Revolution: The Adaptation of the People of Japan to a New Day. Chapters 6-7. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Operational Field of the Employment and Manpower Services." Brookings Institution, Employment Service Conferences, Conference 3, Washington, DC. February 27, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Oslo - Yale Sporreskjema Utarbeidet." With Rolf Wattne, Arne Ebeltoft and Gunnar Wegge. (Box 3, Folder 15a)
  - "Papers Relative to Development and Uses of Power." 1. "Organizational Basis of Relative Power." 2. "Status, Rank, and Role." 3. "Organizational Factors in Productivity." (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Patterns of Leadership and their Characteristics." Table. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Une Politique Active de Main-D'oeuvre." Rapport No. 1, Seminaire Patronal International sur une Politique Active de Main-D'oeuvre, Division des Affaires Sociales, OCDE, Bruxelles, 14-17 Avril, 1964. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Preliminary Report on Barter Exchange and Scrip." February 22 1933. (See also Producers' Exchanges.) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Principles of Adaptive Human Behavior." First Draft. May 1946. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "The Problem Solving Process." (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Producers' Exchanges: A Report Prepared for the New Haven Committee on Unemployment Relief, New Haven Connecticut. March 22, 1933. (See also "Preliminary Report on Barter Exchange and Script".) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "A Project of Research, Training and Publication related to Organizational Behavior." (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Public Employment Offices and Unemployment Insurance Systems: Some Hazards in Their Association." Employment Service News 2 (October 1935): 3-6. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "The Public Interest in Labor and Management Disputes." Speech and Discussion. Pennsylvania Water Works Association Proceedings of the Fifty-Second Annual Meeting, October 13, 14, and 15, 1948. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Raisons Economiques et Sociales d'une Politique Active de la Main-D'oeuvre. Rapport No. 1, Seminaire Syndical International sur la Politique Active de la Main-D'oeuvre. Division des Affaires Sociales, OCDE, Vienne, Septembre 17-20, 1963. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Review of Kreps Manuscript." [on the status of women in the labor force] (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - A review of Social and Economic Security, by Sir William Beveridge. The Yale Review 32 (Spring 1943): 585-589. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Sermons. Some transcribed by "Alma Mac T..." and edited by Bakke. 1929-1930 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29-32)
  - [Social Insurance.] (Paper is without an indicated title.) (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Some Papers Relative to Structure and Dynamics of Unions as Organizations." 1. "Concept of Social Organization." 2. "Maintenance of Organizational Stability and Viability." 3. "Evidences of Effectiveness of Bonds of Organization." 4. "Labor Organizations." 5. "Fusion Process." (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Status of the Employment Services." Brookings Institution, Conference 2. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "Steps in the Problem - Solving Process and the Intended Consequences of Each Step." January 1955. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Student Movements, Appendix A" and hand-written notes. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - "Student Protests." The Encyclopedia of Education 2: 241-47. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - "Student Protests." Draft. (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Students on the March. Chapters 1-4. Manuscript and Typescript draft. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Students on the March. Chapter 5. Manuscript and Typescript draft. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Students on the March. Chapter 5. Typescript draft. (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Students on the March. Chapter 6. Typescript draft. (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Students on the March. Chapter 8. Typescript draft. (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Students on the March. Chapter 9. Typescript draft. (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Students on the March. Chapter 9. Photocopy draft. (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Students on the March. Sections 1 and 2. (Box 3, Folder 47-48)
  - Students on the March. Section 3. (Box 3, Folder 49-50)
  - Students on the March. Section 4. (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Students on the March. Section 5. (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - "Students on the March, the Case of Japan." Preliminary Draft, October 1964. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Students on the March, the Cases of Mexico and Colombia." Preliminary Draft. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Tasks and Acts Incorporated in the Organizational Process." (Taken from Telephone Company Operations). February 1959. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Thomas Industries Executives memorandum from Bakke on evaluation of key personnel. April 1959. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Training for Tactics." In Training Moves Ahead. Proceeding of the Fifth Annual Convention of the American Society of Training Directors. Cleveland, OH, March 3-5, 1949. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Unemployed Man and Insurance or Dole. Interview Questions, 1931-1932. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Unemployment and Social Security." In Seventh International Management Congress. Washington D.C. September 19-23, 1938. National Management Council of the USA. Baltimore: Waverly Press, Inc. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 1958. Uomini ed Organizzazione: Il Processo di Fusione. Collana di Studi sul Lavoro, a cura dell'Istituto per l'Addestramento nell'Industria e dell'Istituto di Studi sul Lavoro. Milano: Edizioni Consulente delle Aziende, 1958. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Ways of Looking at Groups." (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "The Work of the Yale University Labor and Management Center." Social Science 24 (April 1949): 73-78. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "What Value has Basic Research in Human Relations?" An address prepared for and delivered at The Dinner Meeting of the Economic Relations Committee, American Friends Service Committee, November 15, 1950. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "What's Ahead in Industrial Relations." In Eastern Water Company Conference 1961 Annual Meeting, Reports and papers presented at the 65th annual meeting, Atlantic City, NJ, October 17-20, 1961. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Folders deleted. (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Articles about E. W. Bakke. (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
- Series V. Subject files.
  Includes notes, reports, pamphlets, reviews and publications by other authors.
  - Conflict. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Faculty participation in academic governance. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Industrial relations research. (Box 4, Folder 23)